上节我们看了一个利用补齐神谕的攻击
In the last segment, we looked at a
padding oracle attack that completely
这个攻击完全破解了认证加密系统。我希望这个攻击能说服大家
breaks an authenticated encryption system.
I hope this attack convinces you that you
(严格地说，是错误实现的认证加密系统)
不要自己去实现认证加密
shouldn't implement authenticated
encryption on your own cause you might end
因为你有可能被补齐神谕或计时攻击等等暴露了
up exposing yourself to a padding oracle
attack or a timing attack or any other
你应当使用类似GCM等标准
such attack. Instead you should be using
standards like GCM or any other of the
或者其他认证加密模式，有很多密码学库实现了它们
standardized authenticated encryption
modes as implemented in many crypto
本节，我将为大家展示另外一个非常聪明的
针对认证加密系统的攻击
libraries. In this segment, I'm gonna show
you another very clever attack on an
我希望在大家看了这个攻击后
authenticated encryption system. And I
hope after you see this attack, you'll be
可以完全说服大家不要自己去发明、实现认证加密系统
completely convinced not to invent and
implement your own authenticated
大家一定要使用标准机制中的一种
encryption systems. But instead, always
use one of the standard schemes, like GCM
比如GCM或其他。那么我想给大家看的这个攻击
or others. So this particular attack that
I want to show you is an attack on the SSH
是针对SSH的二元数据包协议的。那么SSH是一个
标准的安全远程shell应用
binary packet protocol. So SSH is a
standard secure remote shell application
使用了一个客户端与服务端之间的协议
that uses a protocol between a client
and the server. It has a key exchange
它有一个密钥交换机制，一旦双方交换密钥，
SSH使用所谓的二元数据包协议
mechanism and once two sides exchange keys,
SSH uses what's called the binary packet
来在客户端和服务端之间相互发送信息
protocol to send messages back and forth
between the client and the server. Now
SSH是这样工作的：我们说过，SSH使用"加密且MAC"
here is how SSH works, so recall that SSH
uses what we called encrypt-and-MAC. Okay
每个SSH包以一个序列号开头
so technically what happens is every SSH
packet begins with a sequence number, and
然后数据包包含了包的长度，CBC补齐的长度
then the packet contains the packet
length, the length of the CBC pad, the
然后是封装数据，接着是CBC补齐。现在这整个红色块
actual payload follows, then the CBC pad
follows. Now this whole red block here is
是用带链式IV的CBC加密的，所以这对CPA攻击也是脆弱的
CBC encrypted also with a chained IV, so
this is also vulnerable to the CPA attacks
就像我们讨论过的那样。但是整个红色数据包
that we discussed before. But
nevertheless, this whole red packet is
使用CBC加密的。然后计算整个数据包的明文的MAC
encrypted using CBC encryption. And then
the entire clear text packet is MAC-ed.
MAC以明文形式发送，和数据包一起。
那么我希望大家记住
And the MAC is sent in the clear, along
with the packet. So I want you to remember
这个MAC是根据数据包的明文计算的，
然后MAC是以明文形式发送的
that the MAC is computed over plain text
packets, and then the MAC is sent in the
这是我们说的"加密且MAC"。我们说过这不是一个好办法
clear. This is what we call encrypt-and-MAC.
And we said that this is not a good
因为MAC没有私密性的要求
way to do things, because MACs have no
confidentiality requirements. And by sending
通过以明文的形式发送明文的MAC，有可能
暴露了明文的信息
the MAC of the clear text in the clear,
you might be exposing information about
但这不是我这里想给大家看的错误
the clear text. But this is not the
mistake that I want to show you here. I
我想给大家看一个聪明得多的攻击。
首先，我们看SSH如何解密
want to show you a much more clever attack.
So first, let's look at how decryption
首先，服务器只解密加密的数据包的
works in SSH. So what happens is, first of
all, the server decrypts the encrypted
包长度域。那么它只解密开头这几个字节
packet length field only. So it only
decrypts these particular first few bytes.
然后它从网络接着读取数据，读取的字节数
Then it will go ahead and read from the
network, as many bytes as specified in the
由数据包长度域指定。SSH使用CBC解密剩下的密文内容
packet length field. It's gonna decrypt the
remaining cipher text blocks using CBC
一旦恢复了整个SSH数据包
decryption. Then, once it's recovered the
entire SSH packet, it will go ahead and
它会接着检查明文的MAC，如果MAC无效，就报错
check the MAC of the plain text, and
report an error if the MAC happens to be
这里的问题是，数据包长度域被解密了
invalid. Now the problem here is that the
packet length field is decrypted and then
然后被直接使用，以决定数据包的长度
used directly to determine the length of
the packet before any authentication has
这是在任何认证发生前。事实上，不可能认证
数据包长度域的MAC
taken place. In fact, it's not possible to
verify the MAC of the packet length field
因为我们还没有还原整个数据包
because we haven't recovered the entire
packet yet and as a result we cannot check
所以我们还不能检查MAC。但是，SSH协议在验证MAC之前
就使用了数据包长度
the MAC. But nevertheless the protocol uses
the packet length before verifying that the MAC
实际上这引入了一个非常犀利的攻击
is valid. So it turns out this introduces a
very, very acute attack. And I'm only
我只描述这个攻击的一个非常简化的版本，以表达基本思想
gonna describe a very simplified version
of this attack, just to get the idea
想法如下：假设攻击者截获了一个密文分组
across. So here's the idea. Suppose the
attacker intercepted a particular cipher
即直接用AES加密的分组M
text block, namely the direct AES
encryption of the message block M. And now
现在攻击者想还原这个M。我强调一下
he wants to recover this M. And I
emphasize that this intercepted
这个截获的密文只有一个分组长，一个AES分组
cipher text is only one block length.
It's one AES block. So here's what the
攻击者这么办：向服务器发送一个数据包
attacker is gonna do. Well, he's gonna
send a packet to the server that starts
数据包的开头是正常的，以一个序列号开头
off as normal. It's basically, starts off
with a sequence number and then he's going
然后他把他截获的密文C作为第一个分组，发送给服务器
to inject his captured cipher text as the
first cipher text block that's sent to the
现在，服务器该怎么办？服务器会解密
server. Now, what is the server going to
do? The server is gonna decrypt the first
第一个AES分组的前几个字节，他会把这前几个字节
few bytes of this first AES block and he's
going to interpret the first few bytes as
解读成数据包的长度域。接下来
the length fields of the packet. The next
thing that's gonna happen is, the server
服务器将期待着这么多字节，在验证MAC之前
is gonna expect this many bytes, before it
checks that the MAC is valid. And so what
攻击者将一次只给服务器一个字节
the attacker is gonna do, is, he's gonna
feed the server one byte at a time. So the
这样服务器会一个字节、一个字节地读
server will read one byte, and then
another byte, and then another byte.
最终，服务器会读到长度域里说的那么多的字节
Eventually, the server will read as many
bytes as the length field specifies, at
他会检测MAC是否有效。当然
which point, it will check that the MAC is
valid. And of course, the attacker was
攻击者给服务器的字节都是随便弄的，因此MAC不会通过验证
just feeding the server junk bytes. And as
a result, the MAC is not gonna verify, and
服务器会发送一个MAC错误，但大家发现
the server will send a MAC error. But you
realize that what happened here, the
攻击者在数他发送给服务器多少个字节
attacker was counting how many bytes it
sent to the server. And so it knows
他能严格地知道他发送了多少个字节，
当他接收到了服务器发来的MAC错误
exactly how many bytes were sent at the
time that it receives the MAC error from
这就告诉攻击者，密文C的前32位的解密结果
the server. So that tells it that the
decryption of the first 32 bits of its
正好等于已经发送的字节数
cypher text C are exactly equal to the
number of bytes that were sent before it
在看到MAC错误之前。那么这是一个非常聪明的攻击
saw the MAC error. So this is a very
clever attack. So let me say it one more
我再说一遍以确保清楚。攻击者有一个密文分组C
time to make sure this is clear. So again,
the attacker has a one block cipher text C
他想解密C，我们假定C解密后，得到的明文的高32位
that it wants to decrypt and let's pretend
that when C is decrypted the 32 most
是数字5。在这种情况下
significant bits of the plain text happen
to be the number five. In this case, what
攻击者会看到如下的事情。服务器会解密
the attacker will see, is the following
behavior. The server is gonna decrypt the
挑战分组C，会得到数字5，并把5当作长度域
challenge block c and he's gonna obtain
the number five as the length field. So,
那么现在，攻击者会给服务器一次一个字节
now, the attacker is gonna feed the server
one byte at a time and after the attacker
在攻击者给服务器5个字节后，服务器说：
我刚刚还原了整个数据包
feeds the server five bytes the server
says, hey, I've just recovered the entire
让我检查MAC。MAC很可能是错的
packet, let me check the MAC. The MAC is
likely to be false and, then, it will
服务器会发送一个坏MAC的错误。那么在读了5个字节后
send, bad MAC error. So after five bytes
are read off the network the attacker is
攻击者会看到一个坏MAC的错误，然后攻击者
就知道了解密后的分组的高32位
gonna see a bad MAC error and then the
attacker learns that the most significant
等于数字5。那么
32 bits of the decrypted block is equal to
the number five. So there. So, you just
你知道了C的高32位。那么这是一个非常重要的攻击
learned the 32 most significant bits of
C. So this is a very significant attack,
因为攻击者刚刚知道了密文分组解密后的高32位
because the attacker just learned 32 bits
of the decrypted cipher text block. And
他可以对任何他想要的密文分组实施这个攻击
since he can apply this attack to any
cipher text block he wants, he can
他可以知道一条长信息的每个密文分组的高32位
basically learn the first 32 bits of every
cipher text block in a very long message.
那么这里发生了什么？密码设计里有两个错误
So what just happened here? Well, there
are actually two things that were wrong in
第一个是，解密操作不是原子操作
this design. The first one is the
decryption operation is non-atomic. In
换句话说，解密算法不取整个数据包作为输入
other words, the decryption algorithm
doesn't take a whole packet as input, and
而返回整个明文作为输出，或者返回"拒绝"
respond with a whole plain text as output,
or with the word reject. Instead, the
解密算法部分地解密了密文
decryption algorithm partially decrypts
the cipher text, namely to obtain the
获得了长度域，然后等待指定数量的字节去还原
length field, and then it waits to recover
as many bytes as needed and then it
然后完成了加密过程。这些非原子解密操作
completes the decryption process. So these
nonatomic decryption operations are fairly
是很危险的，一般来说，需要避免使用他们。
在这个例子里，这个非原子操作
dangerous, and generally, they should be
avoided. In this example, this nonatomic
正好破坏了认证加密
decryption happens to break authenticated
encryption. The other problem that
另一个问题在于，在正确地认证之前，就使用了长度域
happened is that the length field was used
before it was properly authenticated. And
这是另一个错误之处，不应该这么做的。
所以加密的数据域不应该被使用
this is another issue that should never be
done. So the encryption field should never
在这个域被正确认证之前。我问大家
be used before the field is actually
authenticated. So let me ask you, if you
如果大家可以重新设计SSH，如何最小地改动这里
had the option of redesigning SSH what is
the minimum change that you would do to
可以让SSH能抵抗这种攻击？我告诉大家
可能有多种答案
make SSH resist this attack? And let me
tell you that multiple answers might be
一个方案是，以明文形式发送一个长度域，就像TLS一样
correct. One option is to send a length
field in the clear, just as in the case of
这样，攻击者没有机会提交选择密文攻击了
TLS. In this case, there's no opportunity
for an attacker to submit chosen cipher
因为长度域不会被加密
text attack, because, well, the length
field is never decrypted. And so there's
这样攻击者无法滥用解密操作
no decryption taking place that the attacker
can abuse. Replacing encrypt-and-MAC
采用"先加密后MAC"而非"加密且MAC"并无影响，
因为这个攻击对于两者都可行的
by encrypt-then-MAC doesn't have any
impact because this attack would apply
问题在于，在认证前，长度域被使用了
either way. The problem is that the length
field is used before it's authenticated
另一种方式也会有这种情况。所以更好的加密模式
and that would have to happen either way.
So a better mode of encryption doesn't
并无裨益。另一种方法是单调对长度域计算MAC
actually help. Another option is to MAC
the length field separately so that now
这样服务器可以读去长度域，检查仅为长度域服务的MAC
the server can read the length field,
check that the MAC for just the length
是否有效，然后服务器就知道了接下来要读多少个字节
field is valid, and then it would know how
many subsequent bytes to read before
之后再检查整个数据包的MAC域。最后一种方案是
checking MAC field on the entire packet.
The last option is actually one that
可行的，但效率极差，可能会让服务器
works, but is terribly inefficient, and it
would expose the server to a denial of
遭受拒绝服务攻击，所以我不认为这是一个有效的答案
service attack, so I'm not going to mark
it as a valid answer. So the main lesson
需要记住的主要的教训是，不要自己去实现
或设计自己的认证加密系统
to remember is, don't implement or design
your own authenticated encryption system.
只使用类似于GCM的密码学标准。但如果出于某些原因
Just use the standards like GCM. But if
for some reason, you can't use the
你不能使用标准，必须实现自己的认证加密系统
standards, and you have to implement your
own authenticated encryption system, then
那么请先加密后MAC。确保不犯这两节里的错误
use encrypt-then-MAC. And make sure not
to repeat the mistakes of the last two
也就是不在认证长度域之前就使用长度域
segments, namely don't use a length field
before the length field is authenticated.
更一般地，不在认证前使用任何解密的域
And more generally, don't use any
decrypted field before that field is
那么我们对认证加密的讨论完结了
authenticated. Okay so this is the end of
our discussion of authenticated
我想指出几篇关于认证加密的论文
encryption. I wanted to point out a couple
of papers on authenticated encryption that
大家可以做进一步的阅读。第一篇很犀利
you could use as further reading. The
first one is a very acute one on the order
是关于加密和认证的先后顺序的，讨论了
是该先加密后MAC
of encryption and authentication that talks
about whether one should do encrypt-then-MAC
还是先MAC后加密，它证实了一个是正确的
or MAC-then-encrypt and it
shows that one is correct and one is
另一个是错误的。此文值得一读，文中信息量很大
incorrect. It's a good read and there's a
lot of information in that paper. The
第二篇讨论了OCB模式，OCB是一个非常有效的
second discusses OCB mode, which is a very
efficient way of building authenticated
构建认证加密的方法。特别地，这篇文章看了
一个带关联数据的OCB的变种
encryption. In particular, it looks at a
variant of OCB with associated data as we
正如我们所讨论过的。最后三篇是关于攻击的论文
discussed when we described OCB. The last
three papers are attack papers. The first
第一篇描述了上节讨论的补齐神谕攻击
one describes the padding oracle attack
that we discussed in the last segment.
这篇描述了这节讨论的长度攻击
This one here describes the length attack
that we just described in this segment.
最后一篇描述了很多对加密机制的攻击
And the last one describes a number of
attacks on encryptions that just use CPA
其中加密机制只用了CPA安全，没有加完整性。
最后一篇提供了很多好例子
security without adding integrity. So this
last paper actually provides a number of
解释了为什么CPA安全本身永远不应该
good examples for why CPA security by
itself should never, ever, ever be used
被用于加密。记住，大家只能使用认证加密
for encryption. Remember the only thing
you're allowed to use is authenticated
来保护私密性。如果大家只需要完整性，不需要私密性
encryption for confidentiality. Or if all
you need is integrity with no
那么用MAC就行了
confidentiality then you just use a MAC.
【伊卡酱 译注】